Hello, world. My name is Professor David J. Malan. I teach computer science at Harvard
and I'm here today to answer your questions from Twitter. This is computer
Science support.
First up, from Tad Proletarian. How do search engines work so
fast? Well, the short answer really is distributed computing,
which is to say that Google and Bing and other such search engines,
they don't just have one server and they don't even have just one really big
server. Rather, they have hundreds, thousands, probably hundreds of
thousands or more servers nowadays around the world. And so when you and
I go to Google or Bing and maybe type in a word to search for,
like cats, it's quite possible that when you hit enter and that
keyword like cats is sent over the Internet to Google or to Bing,
it's actually spread out ultimately across multiple servers, some of
which are grabbing the first 10 results, some of which are grabbing the next 10
results, the next 10 result. So. So that you see just one collection of results.
But a lot of those ideas, a lot of those search results came from different
places. And this eliminates what could potentially be a bottleneck of
sorts if all of the information you needed had to come from one specific
server that might very well be busy. When you have that question, Nick asks,
will computer programming jobs be taken over by AI within the next
5 to 10 years? This is such a frequently asked question nowadays, and I don't
think the answer will be yes. And I think we've seen evidence of this already
in that early on when people were creating websites, they were literally
writing out code in a language called HTML by hand. But then,
of course, software came along, tools like Dreamweaver that you could download on your own
computer that would generate some of that same code for you. More recently, though,
now you can just sign up for websites like Squarespace and WIX and others whereby
click, click, click, and the website is generated for you. So I dare say certainly
in some domains that AI is really just an evolution of that trend.
And it hasn't put humans out of business as much as it has made
you and I much more productive. AI, I think. And the ability soon
to be able to program with natural language is just going to enhance what you
and I can already do logically, but much more mechanically.
And I think too, it's worth considering that there's just so many bugs or mistakes
in software in the world, and there's so many features that humans wish existed
in products present and future, that our to do list,
so to speak, is way longer than we'll ever have time to finish
in our lifetimes. And so I think the prospect of having an artificial
intelligence boost our productivity and work alongside us,
so to speak, as we try to solve problems is just going to mean that
you and I and the world together can solve so many more problems and move
forward together at an even faster rate. Alright, next up,
Sophia, who asks, how do microchips even work? It's just a green
piece of metal. Well, here, for instance, we have a whole bunch of microchips
on which what's called a logic board, or sometimes known as a motherboard. There's a
lot of ports that you might be familiar with. For instance, like here's some
ports for audio, here's some ports for networking, here's some ports for
USB and some other devices as well. And those ports, meanwhile,
are connected to lots of different chips on this board that know how to interpret
the signals from those ports. And perhaps the biggest chip on this motherboard
tends to be this thing here called the CPU or the central processing unit,
which is really the brains of the computer and what you can't necessarily quite see
because most of this is actually paint and not traces. But if I flip this
around, you'll actually see in the right light and with the right angle,
a whole bunch of traces running up, down, left and right on this logic
board that's connecting all of these various microchips. And by trace,
I mean a tiny little wire that's been etched into the
top or the bottom of this circuit board that connects two parts thereon.
Now, what might these microchips be doing? Well, again, they might be simply interpreting
signals that are coming in from these ports. Two, they might be performing
mathematical operations, doing something with those signals in order to convert input
into output, or they might just be storing information ultimately.
In fact, there's all different types of memory on a logic board like this,
be it RAM or ROM or the like. And so some of those chips might
very well be storing information for as long as the computer is plugged in,
or in some cases, depending on the device, even when the power goes
off. Alright, next, a question from Nkhe. So if anyone can learn
coding, what do computer scientists do? For four years in university,
typically in an undergraduate program in computer science,
computer engineering, or a similar field, someone spends
much more time learning about the field itself than about programming specifically.
So as such, you might study not only a bit of programming, but also mathematics,
certain fundamentals that transcend the particular classes you might have
taken in middle school or high school, but that can be used to solve grander
real World problems. You might learn something about networks, how you can
send information from point A to point B. You might learn about graphics, how you
can display things on the screen, or even create interactive animations or
the like. You might learn how to leverage certain ideas from mathematics and
other fields to implement your very own artificial intelligence nowadays,
whereby you use probability and statistics and information more
generally to try to predict what an intelligent individual,
or in this case computer, might say in response to a question. So computer
science itself is a very broad field, and programming is really just a
tool that you tend to learn along the way. For Maya Shelby,
how do zeros and ones turn into the Internet? Well, I think
the simplest answer there is that the Internet is built upon layers and
layers and layers of ideas. And if we start at the lowest of those
levels, zeros and ones, you have something called binary, where zeros and
ones can be used to represent any other numbers as well. And if we
use more and more zeros and ones, more and more binary digits
or bits, so to speak, we can count up higher and higher and higher.
And then if you and I agree that, alright, well, let's not just use these
patterns of zeros and ones to represent numbers, what if we reserve some
of these patterns to represent letters like the English Alphabet, and then
maybe you and I can decide to reserve certain patterns of zeros and ones to
represent colors like red and green and blue and combinations thereof?
Well, once we have the ability to represent colors, we could then represent whole
pictures, because what's a picture on your phone or a computer screen? Well, it's really
just a grid of dots, each of which has its own color. So this
is all to say that even if we start at this lowest level of just
zeros and ones, so long as you and I and all of the devices we
use agree to follow some steps standard like this, we can build these
layers and layers of abstraction, so to speak, on top of one another,
until finally you and I come up with a pattern of zeros and ones that
represent send this piece of information from me over there.
Thus we have something like the Internet.
Can someone that knows computer science explain to me why computers use binary
coding, not trinary? And trinary is supposed to be faster.
So it's not necessarily the case that a trinary system, which would
use three symbols, for instance 0, 1 and 2, would necessarily
be faster than binary, because binary using just zero and one
tends to be simpler to implement and also more robust to
potential error. Or if you're familiar with voltage levels, like in a battery,
it's very easy for a computer to distinguish something like 0
volts or 3 volts, but it gets a little harder if we try to draw
the line somewhere in between, because there's just a higher probability that a
computer might mistake a voltage level like 1.5
in the middle is maybe being a little closer to off than on or
to on than off. Here too is where even though there might be mathematical efficiencies
and real world efficiencies to using trinary, otherwise known as ternary,
like a zero, a one and a two digit instead of just zeros and ones,
it turns out because our world runs on electricity nowadays and there's so
much momentum behind binary that it just tends to be net
positive, rachelp95 asks why is every Windows solution,
have you tried restarting? And why does that always work? So that's
a very heavy handed solution to what are typically just bugs or mistakes in
software. For instance Windows in this case, restarting a computer
just starts everything from scratch. So all of the computer's short term memory
is lost and everything starts in pristine condition. Which is to say that it
starts in exactly the way that the programmers at Microsoft intended, without potentially
the distractions of the computer being in some weird state state or condition that the
programmers just didn't anticipate. Maybe you clicked on some buttons in a weird order,
maybe you opened a strange file, but maybe you got the computer into
a state that just wasn't programmed for properly. Jason Whitmer now asks what's
the best operating system? Well, this is one of these questions in computing we would
call a religious question, since it evokes a religious debate as to
which might be best. Of course, among the most popular operating systems out there are
Windows and macOS, but there's also one you might not have heard of,
which is called called Linux, which is actually very omnipresent in the enterprise
world. So many of today's servers actually run Linux. So many of today's desktops or
laptops though, run Windows or Mac os. Now that's not
to say you couldn't run all of those operating systems in different contexts. And some
of us do actually run Linux on our own computers. So a lot of it
is really boils down to personal preference. I wouldn't even say that there's
one best operating system, but there tend to be correlations between
the operating systems people use and the applications applications they have in mind. So Windows,
for instance, is so popular in the world of PCs and desktops and laptops.
Mac OS is to some Extent, particularly in academia in certain countries,
but not necessarily on the same scale. Linux, by contrast, is again
very much used heavily in the server side industry, but so is
Windows as well. So a lot of the choice for operating systems sometimes comes
from just what's most appropriate, what's most popular, what's most supportive.
But some of it comes too from just personal preference of the engineer, maybe the
first engineer that you hire to make one of those decisions. So it's more about
what's best for you and not so much best in general.
Next, Julio Magnifico asks, why aren't computers getting
cheaper? Well, computers, or at least computer parts
inside of computers, do tend to get cheaper. The catch is that your expectations
and my expectations just keep rising. We want our phones, our laptops,
our desktops to do more and more in the way of the software that they
run, the games that we use, and just how quickly they perform for us.
So even though some of those parts parts are getting less expensive, you and I
want them to do more and more and be faster and larger in quantity.
And so as a result, I dare say that the price isn't going
down as far as you might hope. That said, nowadays you can get for the
same amount of money from yesteryear much, much more in the way of computing
power. So arguably it's working to our benefit in some
cases. Next up from Daro Nabilo. Can someone explain cloud
computing to me like a 5 year old? Cloud computing is
essentially you using someone else's servers that someone is paying to
rent, for instance, or timeshare. So this isn't really a new idea
or new technology. Rather it's a better branding of a technique that's been
used for years, not just in the computer world, but in the real world as
well, whereby someone like Google or Microsoft or Apple or others
nowadays might be able to afford lots and lots and lots of servers and
then make those servers available in part to me, to you and
many other customers as well. Hey, I'm Marcus. Hey,
Marcus. Well, Marcus asks, how does computer memory work?
Think of computer memory as really being driven by a whole bunch of switches that
can either be turned on and off. So for instance, if I take this
here light switch, which is currently off, I could simply say that this
switch here is representing the number 0 in binary. But if I
turn the switch on, well now I can say that I'm representing the number one.
Now of course, I can only count as high as 0 to 1 with
a single light switch, but what if I bring over a Second light
switch, like this one here. If we start at zero in this
way, turn on this switch first and claim that it's
one. Let me now be more creative and turn this one off and this one
on. And now claim this is how a computer's memory could represent
the number two. And now if I turn this switch back on,
giving me a fourth pattern, this is how I might represent the number
three. Now of course, if we add more and more of these switches, more and
more of these light bulbs, we can count even higher than three. And indeed that's
what a computer's memory is ultimately doing. It's using lots
and lots of little tiny switches, otherwise known as transistors,
to turn the flow of electricity on and off. And then it's got other
types of hardware called for instance, capacitors that have a capacity
to hold on to some of that electricity, just like the light bulb there
being on. Alright. Next, Donny asks, how do you explain Web3
to people? So Web3, like Web2
and Wretches respectively, Web1 are really just buzzwords that describe sort
of phases of the Internet or the World Wide Web as you and I know.
For instance, back in the day when there was just the World Wide Web,
now perhaps referred to as Web version 1, information was largely
static. If you were to create a website on the Internet, you would type up
your code, you would type up your content, you would put it on a server
somewhere and someone could read that information. But it was
you, the web developer, or you, the owner of the website
that was creating that content for other people to actually read and consume.
In Web2, the world became much more dynamic in recent years,
whereby now websites tend to have databases and they have more
sophistication, so that a lot of the content in websites today are
actually coming from me and from you. So if you think of any social
media site, it's not the owners of those sites that are creating most of the
content, it's you and me as the users, those same websites.
But in Web2, everything is nonetheless very centralized. Whether you're
Twitter or Facebook now Meta or other companies. All of that data,
even in the world of social media that's coming from me and you,
is actually being stored centrally on those companies servers.
So web 3.0 or web 3, so to speak, is really
about transitioning away potentially from that very centralized
model to one that's more distributed. Where the data that you and
I are creating, whereby the data you and I are consuming is
actually distributed over multiple servers, over a technique
called blockchain for instance, in some cases, whereby there's not necessarily
one owner of that data, but really collective ownership
and therefore verification that the data maybe indeed came from
me and you. Next, a question from can
someone explain to me the difference between firmware and software? Hardware is
physical. Software is code. WTF is firmware?
Firmware is really a synonym for a type of software. So firmware is just
software, but it tends to be software that comes built into
your hardware. And you can think of in the simplest scenario that
firmware is software that is just completely integrated into the hardware
and itself cannot be changed or even upgraded. But that's a bit of an
oversimplification, because even firmware, typically when it comes in a
computer, when it comes in a phone or some other device, can very often
be updated. Why? Because the firmware is the software that's really
closest to the hardware. And in that sense it might very well be the most
important. And if anything goes wrong with the firmware, you might not even be able
to turn that device on, whether it's a phone, a computer, or even your refrigerator
nowadays. All right, that's all the questions for today. We hope you learned a
little something along the way. We'll see you next time.